Ben Somers

Software Developer

somers.ben@gmail.com | http://www.github.com/bensomers

San Francisco, California 210-651-2701

Summary

Versatile and agile engineer, with several years' experience building web applications in Ruby and Ruby on Rails. Preference for full-stack development, opportunities to learn new technologies and problem domains, and flexible and innovative teams with an emphasis on agile methods though not necessarily Agile dogma.

Specialties

Development: Ruby, Rails, Sinatra, jQuery, Python, Java, C, C++

Systems Automation: Chef Deployment: Capistrano Version Control: git, SVN Cloud Services: AWS, Heroku

Experience

Senior Software Engineer, BookRenter, San Mateo, CA

June 2010 – present

Promoted from Software Engineer, April 2012

Developed large-scale e-commerce RoR applications with complex dynamic pricing engine and automated distributor network. Performed product and feature development in close collaboration with business stakeholders and other engineers. Transitioned to DevOps team in July 2011, with an emphasis on Chef for systems automation. Led projects to upgrade five large-scale applications and ~80 backend scripts from Rails 2.3 to 3, and from Ruby 1.8.7 to 1.9. Acquired detailed knowledge of Ruby and Rails internals, as well as details of Passenger and Unicorn webservers and other technology stack components.

Lead Developer, Student Technology Collaborative, Yale University, New Haven CT Summer 2008 – Spring 2010 (1 year 8 months: full-time in summers, part-time otherwise)

Led project team writing RoR department management applications. Responsible for interviewing, selecting, and training new team members, assisting with project management and release scheduling, and full-time development.

Coordinator, **Student Technology Collaborative**, Yale University, New Haven CT Fall 2007 – Spring 2010 (2 and a half years: part-time)

Supervised 4-5 other student employees in university tech support group. Responsible for managing all tech support for approximately 500 students, both in communicating with students, coordinating other technicians and in directly performing repairs.

Education

Yale College, New Haven, Connecticut B.S. in Mechanical Engineering, 2006-2010, 3.4 GPA Coursework equivalent to a minor in Computer Science (no formal minor available)